Finding Aid for the Miriam Matthews photograph collection, 1781-1989 LSC.1889
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Daily Life in Black Los Angeles and California., 1885-1980.
  - Business, Professionals, and Laborers.
    - African American female doctors. (Box 34, Folder 14)
      Includes S.S. Turner (doctor?), Dr. Shelby B. Robinson, and Dr. Lois Gibson.
    - Nurses at Los Angeles County General Hospital. (Box 34, Folder 15)
      Includes photograph of multi-ethnic group of nurses from Los Angeles County General Hospital wearing nurses uniforms from the late 1880s to 1980s, and a portrait of Lois Towns an early black nurse at General Hospital.
    - Black Dentists in Los Angeles. (Box 34, Folder 16)
      Includes portrait of Theodore Banks, Hugh Anthony Bell and Charles Ennis with USC Dental School graduates (different years), and Dr. William Watkins in his dental office.
    - Unidentified Paddle Steamer Boat?. (Box 34, Folder 17)
  - Parades and Cars.
    - Rose Parade., 1901-1908. (Box 17, Folder 7)
      Photographs of crowds and floats at the Pasadena Rose Parade
    - Parades in Early Black Los Angeles., 1895-1910. (Box 17, Folder 8)
      Includes photographs of Fiesta Parade, the Citizen's Band of the Colored YMCA, and other unidentified parades
    - Men and women posing with their cars. (Box 17, Folder 9)
      Includes Angelita Williams, Welcome and John Watson, and police officer Frank White.
    - High School Marching Band and Unidentified Beauty Pageant., undated. (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Educators, Students, and Libraries.
    - Libraries and Librarians. (Box 20, Folder 19)
      Includes photograph of four city librarians (white), Miriam Matthews and other librarians celebrating the 45th anniversary of the Vermont Square Regional Branch Library. Also includes photographs of the Westchester Branch Library, James P. Beckwourth Library (San Diego), Vermont Square Regional Branch Library, the old Watts Library building, and a group of multiracial children in front of the Helen Hunt Jackson Library.
    - Elementary and High School Students. (Box 20, Folder 20)
      Includes photographs of first public school in Los Angeles (1855), an ungraded school in Sacramento (1882), Monrovia school children, a National Youth Administration Work Program, Virginia Stephens' elementary school classes (c. 1914), in Riverside (1938), and some students from unidentified schools. High Schools include Los Angeles H.S. (1905), Hollywood H.S. (1902 and 1907)
    - African American graduates. (Box 21, Folder 1)
      Includes photographs from Crisis Magazine of black graduates from college and graduate school; Samuel Danley as a U.S.C graduate; Ernest Houston Johnson, first black graduate of Stanford University (1891-2), Mamie Cunningham, Los Angeles H.S. graduate (1905), Ruby Offutt
    - Trade School and Technical Classes. (Box 21, Folder 2)
      Includes sloyd or manual training class at Ann Street School (c. 1890-1900), graduating class of 1933 at Wiggins Trade School, and aircraft instruction at Jefferson High School.
    - Los Angeles Chapter of Howard University Alumni Association, 1918. (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Bessie Bruington Burke, first African American teacher and principal in Los Angeles., c. 1910-1955. (Box 21, Folder 4)
      Includes graduation portrait of Bruington upon graduation from Normal School, Burke at middle age, and at retirement in 1955.
    - Bessie Bruington Burke with students and schools. (Box 21, Folder 5)
      Includes Burke with Holmes Avenue School students, and a photograph of a class and male teacher at the 49th Street School where she was principal.
    - Bessie Bruington Burke and family. (Box 21, Folder 6)
      Includes photograph of Bruington residence, Burke residence, Bessie and Ethel (sister) Bruington as young girls, Bessie and Janie (mother) Bruington, Bessie with family on Bruce's Beach, Janie Bruington and Esther Beck.
    - Black educators and teachers in California. (Box 21, Folder 7)
      Includes photograph of Ida Jackson, first certified African American school teacher in California; Sarah Mildred Jones, first black school teacher in Sacramento, and an 1894 petition to retain her as principal; Alice McKinney who taught at a school for black children in Visalia (sister of Mrs. Wiley Hinds, see box 13, folder 2); Holmes Avenue School Teachers; black school principals in 1962; and negative of Jefferson High School PTA photograph.
    - Higher Administration in Education. (Box 21, Folder 8)
      Includes photographs of past and present presidents of Samuel Huston College, a co-educational institution for blacks; four black school principals in Los Angeles; William Easter who worked for the State Department of Education; Los Angeles County Democratic Club, organized in 1937 to support Fay Allen for the Board of Education; photographs of Arthur Prince, district superintendent for Enterprise School District; Lloyd Dickey, Willowbrook School District Superintendent; Wilson Riles, formerly California Superintendent of Schools and first African American to be elected to statewide office in California.
  - Military Officers and Soldiers.
    - USC Student Army Training Corps, Company A (negative). (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - U.S. Army Officers, including Leon Marsh., 1917-1918. (Box 19, Folder 10)
      Includes negatives of Fifth Provisional Company Officers Reserve Training Camp in Fort Des Moines Iowa, and Commissioned Officers of 317th Engineers. See box 10, folders 24-27 for more of Marsh family.
    - David Bennett Hundley, in Spanish American War Uniform., c. 1898. (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Drawing of Crispus Attucks, first person shot at Boston Massacre., 1770. (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - African American Officers in World War I., c. 1917-1918. (Box 19, Folder 13)
      Included in group photograph: Lieut. Harry W. Sheppard, Lieut. Norman O. Houston, Lieut. John Wynn, Lieut. Clay E. Hunter, Lieut. George W. Washington
    - Norman O. Houston in World War I uniform., c. 1917-1918. (Box 19, Folder 14)
      Houston later became a Los Angeles businessman and president of Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company.
    - Certificate of Service Discharge for James Tribble., 1866. (Box 19, Folder 15)
      Photographic print of this document
    - Henry O. Flipper, first black West Point graduate, and his wife. (Box 19, Folder 16)
      Individual portraits of both Henry O. Flipper and his wife.
    - Tenth Cavalry of the U.S. Army, one of original "Buffalo Soldier" units. (Box 19, Folder 17)
      Includes photographs of Col. James Beck (who went over the top of San Juan Hill with Theodore Roosevelt), the 10th Cavalry in Leavenworth, Kansas, and a member of the 10th at 93 years old.
    - Frank Gagnet, U.S. Navy World War I., 1917-1918. (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - Unidentified Military Officer (World War II?). (Box 19, Folder 19)
      Photographed by Frank Cloud?
    - S.S. James Weldon Johnson, Liberty Ship of World War II., 1942. (Box 19, Folder 20)
      Liberty Ship of World War II named for author, civil rights activist, and first executive secretary of the NAACP. Charlotta Bass christened the ship during World War II.
    - Skippy Smith, headed a company making pilot chutes during World War II., 1930s. (Box 19, Folder 21)
      Photograph of Skippy with his partner "Skip" Gravelle who was killed in 1939
    - United Service Organizations. (Box 19, Folder 22)
      Harriet Tubman Auxiliary of the Red Cross (1919), United Service Organizations Negro Red Cross volunteers (WWII)
    - Fort McArthur, Visitor's Day., 1940. (Box 19, Folder 23)
      Citizen's Military Training Camp. Group includes: J.T. Green, Charles Matthews, Norman O. Houston and others.
    - Black Military Aviation. (Box 19, Folder 30)
      Includes photograph of black men in Army Air Forces, and U.S. Navy pilots
  - Sports, Recreation, and Leisure.
    - Black Aviation., 1930s. (Box 19, Folder 29)
      Includes photographs of C.A. "Chief" Anderson, Dr. Albert E. Forsythe, Hubert Julian, J. Herman Banning, Thomas Allen, the Western Flying School of Aeronautics, aircraft and aeronautics classes at Jefferson High School, Craftsmen of Black Wings
    - Rose Bowl., 1982. (Box 19, Folder 25)
    - Golf. (Box 19, Folder 26)
      Includes photograph of an advertisement for West Coast Golf Club's tournament at Griffith Park, and a page on the Parkridge Country Club in Corona from Western Progress magazine in 1928.
    - Sports pages from University of California yearbook., undated. (Box 19, Folder 27)
      From estate of Virginia Stephens.
    - Lucky Baldwin's racehorse, black jockey., c. 1885. (Box 19, Folder 28)
      Horse Volante won the American Derby in 1885.
    - Bessie Coleman, first female pilot of African descent. (Box 20, Folder 1)
      Includes several photographs with flight gear and plane, promotional ads, photograph with her instructor Robert Thelen in Germany, and a print of her international pilot's license issued in France, 1921.
    - Bessie Coleman's family. (Box 20, Folder 2)
      Includes names and dates copied from the Coleman family Bible, a photograph of Bessie's sisters Nilus and Elois, and photograph of her mother Susan Coleman shown with Bessie's cup in 1922.
    - Johnny Riddle, USC football halfback., 1922-1924. (Box 20, Folder 3)
      Photograph and brief description of Riddle's athleticism.
    - Giants baseball team, African American., undated. (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Westside Tennis Club Annual Tournament (negative)., 1917. (Box 20, Folder 5)
      at Santa Monica High School
    - Hollywood High School Football Team., 1908. (Box 20, Folder 6)
      Includes one African American player and one Asian American player.
    - Whittier College Varsity Football Team., 1928. (Box 20, Folder 7)
      Includes one African American player, Nathaniel George.
    - Walter Gordon, assistant coach of football team for University of California, Berkeley., 1925. (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Hostesses for the Haitian Olympic Team, Los Angeles., 1932. (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - USC track and field athletes, including O.J Simpson., c. 1967. (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Emmett Ashford, First Major League Black Baseball Umpire., c. 1970. (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Jackie Robinson, First Black Major League Baseball Player since 1880., `1939-1957. (Box 20, Folder 12)
      Includes photograph of Jackie Robinson and two other black UCLA football players, Woody Strode and Kenny Washington (with Ray Bartlett they were the first black football players for UCLA in 1939). Also includes a photograph of Robinson with Pasadena Junior college team, a photograph of Robinson with Ray Bartlett in Honolulu where they played on a semi-professional integrated team (1941), and a photograph of Robinson speaking at the Oakland Civic Auditorium (1957).
    - Joe Louis, boxer. (Box 20, Folder 13)
      Portrait of Joe Louis who lived in Los Angeles after he retired from boxing.
    - Black Cowboys and Rodeo. (Box 20, Folder 14)
      Photographs of black cowboys on horses, with cattle, and riding bucking broncos.
    - Brice Taylor, first All-American football player at USC, and one of first African Americans on the same team., 1925-1926. (Box 20, Folder 15)
      Includes page from unidentified magazine reporting his position has president of Guadalupe Junior College in Seguin, Texas. Also includes a photograph of Taylor with Senator Edward Brooke and two others.
    - Recreation and Leisure, African American adults and families., 1896-1948. (Box 20, Folder 16)
      Includes group of young African American women on Catalina Island (1922), Mr. and Mrs. Murray in front of their dude ranch in Victorville, Dr. Thomas Nelson and his boat (1907), a group in a surrey with a fringed top, a Tally-Ho Party (1902), Los Angeles' Speed Burners at Sycamore Grove (1896), a fishing trip to Ensenada, a company picnic given by Bullock's Department Store for their black employees and families, and several other picnic scenes. Also includes photographs and negatives of Titus Alexander and friends at a California mission, in Wawona, and on a picnic with Joe and Charlotta Bass.
    - Bruce's Beach., 1910s-1920s. (Box 20, Folder 17)
      Includes photographs of African American men and women recreating on Bruce's Beach in Manhattan Beach. It was one of the few beaches not off-limits to African Americans at this time. White opposition to Bruce's beach increased as the black population grew and coastal land became more valuable. It was condemned and the African American community was forced out. Also see photograph of women from Delta Sigma Theta sorority at Manhattan Beach in box 24, folder 8.
    - Recreation and Leisure, African American children and teenagers. (Box 20, Folder 18)
      Includes photographs of children playing and picnicking in Sycamore Canyon, Glendale, unidentified children in front of their house, school children attending an afternoon movie on Central Ave., and a group of teenager on a hike on Mt. Wilson in 1922. Children at a Sunday School picnic.
  - Police, Sheriff, Fire, Postal.
    - "Blacks in Los Angeles Fire Department" Binder. (Box 29, Folder 7)
      Includes photographs from a binder compiled by Miriam Matthews
    - "Los Angeles Police Department" Binder. (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Los Angeles Fire Department photos, from El Pueblo de Los Angeles. (Box 29, Folder 9)
      Includes photographs of Hose Co. #4 near First Street and Chemical Engine Co. #1 near First Street.
    - Los Angeles Fire Department, Engine Companies and Truck Companies. (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Los Angeles Fire Department, Hose Companies. (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Engine Company from Oakland Fire Department. (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Committee for Police and Fire improvement., 1927. (Box 29, Folder 13)
      Includes photograph of the committee in backyard of Fire Department Engine Company #30 at 14th and Central. All persons are members of fire department except one.
    - Fire Department in Parades., c. 1909. (Box 29, Folder 14)
      Includes photograph of firemen's float in 1909, and an unidentified parade.
    - Fireman, Thomas Collier. (Box 29, Folder 15)
      Includes photographs of Collier with fire engines, and his funeral after he was killed in the line of duty.
    - Retirement of Fireman, Arnett Hartsfield. (Box 29, Folder 16)
      Includes negative photographs of retirement dinner and banquet for Hartsfield.
    - Fire Stations and groups of Fire Fighters. (Box 30, Folder 1)
      Includes photographs of Loma Drive Fire Station (1915), group of firemen at 14th and Central Ave., negative of photograph Captain John Powell, George Bright and Edward Bowen with a horse, photograph of fire department in San Diego.
    - Morgan (Georgia) Robinson, first black female police officer in Los Angeles. (Box 30, Folder 2)
      Includes portraits of Robinson as a young woman, with colleagues, and as an elderly woman in her garden.
    - Groups of Los Angeles Police Officers. (Box 30, Folder 3)
      Includes photographs of police officers, including the "Strong Men", and Detective Bureau. Also group with Allen Allensworth (see box 5 folders 2-7 for more on Allensworth).
    - Los Angeles Police Department, Traffic Division., c. 1909-1914. (Box 30, Folder 4)
      Includes photograph of Traffic Division in 1914 (including one black police officer) and a black officer directing traffic after the Los Angeles Times building.
    - Individual Police Officers. (Box 30, Folder 5)
      Includes photographs and negatives of Officer Randolph, Detective Lieutenant Jesse L. Kimborough, Detective Lieutenant Robert Green, Detective Lieutenant Homer Garrott, Lieutenant Littleton McDuff, William Glenn, Robert Stewart, and Frank White.
    - Los Angeles Police Commission, including Charles Matthews., 1946-1950. (Box 30, Folder 6)
      Includes photograph of Charles Matthews, first black police commissioner, and other members of the commission.
    - Leslie Shaw, Los Angeles Postmaster., 1963. (Box 30, Folder 7)
      Includes photograph of Leslie Shaw being sworn in as postmaster of Los Angeles (by Mayor Sam Yorty?)
    - Aaron Arthur Jenkins, mail carrier, and family., c. 1894, 1930. (Box 30, Folder 8)
      Includes photograph of Aaron Jenkins in uniform, and portrait of his sister Pauline Jenkins
    - Ma-Po-Fi Social Club., 1947. (Box 30, Folder 9)
      Includes photograph of club for Mailmen, Policemen, and Firemen at the first annual ball in Los Angeles
    - Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department. (Box 30, Folder 10)
      Includes photograph of Julius Boyd Loving, first black deputy sheriff in Los Angeles county (1909); William Darden as first black captain (1966); Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department in 1948; Arthur McClanahan receiving scroll for his service as County Bailiff upon his retirement and Sheriff Eugene Biscailuz riding a horse
    - Group of Los Angeles Postal Clerks. (Box 30, Folder 11)
      Included in group was Los Angeles' first postal clerk of color.
    - San Diego Post Office., 1915-1950s. (Box 30, Folder 12)
      Includes negative photographs of black postal carriers in San Diego.
  - Street Scenes.
    - Early Views of Downtown Los Angeles., c. 1869-1900. (Box 17, Folder 1)
      Includes photographs of early business districts (particularly those owned by the Mason and Owens families), City Hall, the Plaza, streetcar terminals, and panoramic views.
    - Early Views of Residential Los Angeles, and outskirts., c. 1868-1900. (Box 17, Folder 2)
      Includes photographs of Western Avenue, Pico Boulevard, Victoria Park Circle, and other early residential areas.
    - Scenes on Central Avenue. (Box 17, Folder 3)
      From the 1920s to the 1950s, Central Avenue was the heart of the African American community and an important scene in the jazz world. Photograph subjects include a youth jazz band, the business district, crowds in front of a movie theater, and a scene from the Watts Riot.
    - Later Los Angeles Street Scenes., 1930-1960. (Box 17, Folder 4)
      Includes photographs of residential areas, streetcars, protests, and beauty pageants.
    - Street Scenes Outside Los Angeles. (Box 17, Folder 5)
      Includes photographs and drawings of San Francisco, Santa Barbara, and unidentified locations.
    - Maps and Demography of Los Angeles. (Box 17, Folder 6)
      Includes photographic prints of a map showing ranchos owned by individuals of African descent (1784-1810), map of Los Angeles business district, a table analyzing the growth of minority group population in Los Angeles, maps depicting distribution of blacks and black voters, a map depicting residential restrictions.
- Black Photographers., 1947-1970.
  Photographs by journalist photographers Frank H. Cloud and Harry H. Adams.
  - Frank H. Cloud., n.d.
    - Individual Portraits. (Box 42, Folder 9)
      Includes many unidentified subjects as well as Amy Peake, Mrs. Augustus Thompson, Frank Cloud Jr., young boy from Atkinson family, and a debutante
    - Advertisement for Golden State Milk?. (Box 42, Folder 10)
      Photograph of baby holding a bottle of Golden State Milk.
    - Clubs and Social Events. (Box 42, Folder 11)
      Includes Town Club members on fishing trip in Ensenada, Mexico and party at home of Ruth Sykes Webster.
    - Weddings. (Box 42, Folder 12)
      Includes Bratton family; William Jones and his Jayda Garland; and an unidentified couple.
    - Portraits of Frank Cloud Sr., photographer. (Box 42, Folder 13)
    - Gregory and Benjamin Cloud (relatives of Frank Cloud Sr.?). (Box 42, Folder 14)
  - Harry H. Adams., 1960-1970.
    - Journalists., 1963-1967. (Box 35, Folder 1)
      Includes photographs of Louis Lomax, George Schuyler, and other unidentified journalists.
    - Africans., 1960-1964. (Box 35, Folder 2)
      Includes groups of African and African American leaders.
    - Malcolm X., 1960-1963. (Box 35, Folder 3)
      Two photographs with groups of black men.
    - Martin Luther King Jr., 1963-1967. (Box 35, Folder 4)
      Includes individual portraits of King, photographs of him speaking or on stage with other speakers, and photographs with community leaders.
    - Robert F. Kennedy. (Box 35, Folder 5)
      Includes photographs of Kennedy speaking, and meeting with black community leaders.
    - Tom Bradley, Mayor of Los Angeles. (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Hubert Humphrey, Vice President. (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Julian Bond, civil rights leader. (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - Lyndon B. Johnson, Vice President. (Box 35, Folder 9)
    - Ted Kennedy, U.S. Senator., 1964, 1966. (Box 35, Folder 10)
    - Nelson Rockefeller as Presidential Candidate. (Box 35, Folder 11)
    - Church leaders and buildings (1 of 2). (Box 35, Folder 12)
      Including building funds, memorials, anniversary dinners, church conferences, congregations, ministers and bishops.
    - Church leaders and buildings (2 of 2. (Box 35, Folder 13)
    - Street Scenes. (Box 35, Folder 14)
      Includes photographs of black community and Los Angeles Police Department, crowds in front of movie theaters, residential areas, Central Avenue, car accidents, parades.
    - Politics and Civil Rights (1 of 2). (Box 36, Folder 1)
      Includes photographs of Martin Luther King Jr., John F. Kennedy, Danny Thomas, Teddy Kennedy, Edmund Brown, Tom Bradley,
    - Politics and Civil Rights (2 of 2). (Box 36, Folder 2)
      Political and Civil Rights leaders
    - Archie Moore, Civil Rights. (Box 36, Folder 3)
      Includes photographs of community event for boys at Archie Moore's Salt Mine training camp, and photographs of political and civil rights leaders.
    - Civil Rights leaders and demonstrations (1 of 2). (Box 36, Folder 4)
      Includes photographs of Dick Van Dyke and Martin Luther King Jr. speaking together at the Los Angeles Coliseum, community members examining a burned cross on a black family home, Martin Luther King Jr., Malcolm X, picketing, voting registration drives, memorial for Medgar Evers.
    - Civil Rights leaders and demonstrations (2 of 2). (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Civil Rights Protests. (Box 36, Folder 6)
      Includes photographs of picketing and protests for civil rights in Los Angeles.
    - Politics., 1959-1967. (Box 37, Folder 1)
      Includes photographs of political leaders, many unidentified and undescribed.
    - Politics and Civil Rights (3 of 3)., 1959-1967. (Box 37, Folder 2)
      Includes photographs of Martin Luther King Jr., Richard Nixon, John F. Kennedy, Roy Wilkins, Edmund Brown, Dianne Carroll, Los Angeles Mayors, other civil rights leaders and church leaders,
    - Campaigning in Los Angeles., 1960-1966. (Box 37, Folder 3)
      Includes photographs of Presidential campaign for John F. Kennedy, Nelson Rockefeller, California Democratic Delegation, Councilman Gilbert Lindsay.
    - Edmund "Pat" Brown, governor of California., 1962. (Box 37, Folder 4)
      Includes photographs of Pat Brown making political visits with black community leaders
    - Community and Political Leaders (1 of 6)., 1959-1967. (Box 37, Folder 5)
      Includes photographs with Tom Bradley, Loren Miller, business, community, club, and political leaders in Los Angeles.
    - Community and Political Leaders (2 of 6)., 1959-1967. (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Community and Political Leaders (3 of 6)., 1959-1967. (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Community and Political Leaders (4 of 6)., 1959-1967. (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Community and Political Leaders (5 of 6)., 1959-1967. (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Community and Political Leaders (6 of 6)., 1959-1967. (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - M. Earl Grant, Family Savings and Loan., 1961-1966. (Box 38, Folder 4)
      Includes photographs of founder M. Earl Grant at various events for Family Savings and Loan
    - Business, Professions, Labor (1 of 3). (Box 38, Folder 5)